As a kid, I used to dream about the ocean.
عندما كنت طفلا صغيرا، كنت أحلم دائما بالمحيط.
It was this wild place full of color and life,
لقد كان ذلك المكان البرّي المليء بالألوان والحياة،
home to these alien-looking, fantastical creatures.
موطن لتلك الكائنات الغريبة الخياليّة.
I pictured big sharks ruling the food chain
لقد صوّرت أسماك القرش الكبيرة المهيمنة على السلسلة الغذائيّة
and saw graceful sea turtles dancing across coral reefs.
ورأيت سلاحف البحر الرشيقة ترقص حول الشعاب المرجانية.
As a marine biologist turned photographer,
كاختصاصي في علم الأحياء البحرية أصبحت مصورا،
I've spent most of my career looking for places
قضيت معظم مسيرتي المهنية أبحث عن الأماكن
as magical as those I used to dream about when I was little.
السحرية كتلك التي كنت أحلم بها عندما كنت صغيرا.
As you can see,
كما ترون،
I began exploring bodies of water at a fairly young age.
لقد بدأت باكتشاف المسطحات البحرية في سن مبكّرة نسبيّا.
But the first time I truly went underwater,
ولكن المرة الأولى التي غصت فيها في أعماق المياه،
I was about 10 years old.
كنت في العاشرة من عمري.
And I can still vividly remember furiously finning
ومازلت أتذكّر جيّدا عندما كنت أسبح بشراسة
to reach this old, encrusted cannon on a shallow coral reef.
للوصول إلى ذلك المدفع القديم المكسوّ بالشعاب المرجانيّة الضحلة.
And when I finally managed to grab hold of it,
وعندما تمكنت أخيرا من الوصول إليه،
I looked up, and I was instantly surrounded by fish
نظرت إلى فوق، لقد كانت تحيط بي الأسماك من كل مكان
in all colors of the rainbow.
بجميع ألوان قوس قزح.
That was the day I fell in love with the ocean.
كان ذلك اليوم الذي وقعت فيه في حبّ المحيط.
Thomas Peschak
توماس بيشاك
Conservation Photographer
مصوّر فوتغرافي للمحافظة
In my 40 years on this planet,
في الأربعين من عمري على هذا الكوكب،
I've had the great privilege to explore
سنحت لي الفرصة لأكتشف
some of its most incredible seascapes
بعض المناظر البحريّة المذهلة
for National Geographic Magazine
لمجلة ناشيونال جوغرافيك
and the Save Our Seas Foundation.
ومؤسّسة احموا بحورنا.
I've photographed everything from really, really big sharks
لقد قمت بتصوير كلّ شيء من أسماك القرش الضخمة
to dainty ones that fit in the palm of your hand.
إلى تلك الصغيرة التي تتناسب مع راحة يدي.
I've smelled the fishy, fishy breath of humpback whales
لقد استنشقت الرائحة المريبة للحيتان الحدباء
feeding just feet away from me
والتي كانت تتغذّى على بعد قدم منّي
in the cold seas off Canada's Great Bear Rainforest.
بالبحار الباردة بكندا بشط الغابة المطيرة للدب العظيم".
And I've been privy to the mating rituals of green sea turtles
ولقد كنت مطلعاً على طقوس التزاوج للسلاحف الخضراء البحرية
in the Mozambique Channel.
بمضيق موزمبيق.
Everyone on this planet affects and is affected by the ocean.
كلّ شخص على هذا الكوكب يتأثر بالمحيط ويُؤثّر فيه.
And the pristine seas I used to dream of as a child
ولقد أصبحت البحار العريقة والنظيفة التي حلمت بها كطفل
are becoming harder and harder to find.
من الصعب جدّا إيجادها.
They are becoming more compressed
لقد أصبحت البحار تشهد ضغطاً أكبر
and more threatened.
ومهدّدة أكثر.
As we humans continue to maintain our role
نحن كبشر مازلنا نُحافظ على دورنا
as the leading predator on earth,
كروّاد الإفتراس على الأرض،
I've witnessed and photographed many of these ripple effects firsthand.
لقد شهدت وصورت العديد من هذه الآثار المباشرة.
For a long time, I thought I had to shock my audience
لمدة طويلة، فكرت في أن أصدم جمهوري
out of their indifference with disturbing images.
بلامبالاتهم من خلال بعض الصور المزعجة.
And while this approach has merits,
وعلى الرغم من أن هذا النهج لديه مزايا،
I have come full circle.
إلا أنني عدت إلى بادئ الأمر.
I believe that the best way for me to effect change
أُؤمن أن أحسن طريقة للتغيير
is to sell love.
هي بيع الحبّ.
I guess I'm a matchmaker of sorts
أعتقد أنني ألعب دور "الخاطب" نوعا ما
and as a photographer,
وكمصوّر فوتغرافي،
I have the rare opportunity
لدي فرصة نادرة
to reveal animals and entire ecosystems
للكشف على الحيوانات والأنظمة الإيكولوجية برمتها
that lie hidden beneath the ocean's surface.
التي تكمن تحت سطح المحيط.
You can't love something and become a champion for it
لا تستطيع أن تقع في حبّ شيء وتصبح بطلاً له
if you don't know it exists.
إذا كنت لا تعلم أنه موجود.
Uncovering this -- that is the power of conservation photography.
بالكشف عن هذا-- هذه قوّة التصوير الفوتغرافي للمحافظة.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
I've visited hundreds of marine locations,
لقد زرت المئات من المواقع البحرية،
but there are a handful of seascapes
ولكن بضعة مناظر بحريّة فقط
that have touched me incredibly deeply.
قد شدّت انتباهي وكان لها تأثير عميق.
The first time I experienced that kind of high
أول مرّة اختبرت فيها ذلك الارتفاع
was about 10 years ago,
كانت حوالي قبل 10 سنوات،
off South Africa's rugged, wild coast.
قبالة سواحل جنوب إفريقيا الوعرة والبرية.
And every June and July,
وفي يونيو ويوليو،
enormous shoals of sardines travel northwards
تٌسافر أسراب هائلة من السردين إلى الشمال
in a mass migration we call the Sardine Run.
في هجرة جماعيّة ما نُسمّيه "هروب السردين".
And boy, do those fish have good reason to run.
وتلك الأسماك لديها سبب وجيه للهروب.
In hot pursuit are hoards of hungry and agile predators.
حيث يتمّ مطاردتها من قبل الحيوانات المفترسة والرشيقة.
Common dolphins hunt together
تصطاد الدلافين بطريقة مشتركة
and they can separate some of the sardines from the main shoal
وتستطيع أن تقوم بتفريق سرب من أسماك السردين
and they create bait balls.
لتخلق مجموعات صغيرة ومُغرية من السمك.
They drive and trap the fish upward against the ocean surface
تقوم باستدراج السمك إلى سطح المحيط
and then they rush in to dine
ثم يسرعون لتناول العشاء
on this pulsating and movable feast.
للاحتفال.
Close behind are sharks.
ويعتقد بأن أسماك القرش وراء ذلك.
Now, most people believe
والآن، يعتقد أغلب الناس
that sharks and dolphins are these mortal enemies,
بأن كلّ من أسماك القرش والدلافين هي أعداء قاتلة،
but during the Sardine Run, they actually coexist.
ولكن خلال "هروب السردين"، فإنها في الواقع تتعايش.
In fact, dolphins actually help sharks feed more effectively.
في الحقيقة، تُساعد الدلافين أسماك القرش لتتغذّى بفعاليّة.
Without dolphins, the bait balls are more dispersed
من دون مساعدة الدلافين، تكون كرات الطعام منتشرة أكثر
and sharks often end up with what I call a sardine donut,
وغالبا ما ينتهي الأمر بأسماك القرش بتناول ما يُسمّى بدونات السردين،
or a mouth full of water.
أو بفم مليء بالماء.
Now, while I've had a few spicy moments with sharks on the sardine run,
حاليّا، بعد أن واجهت لحظات مثيرة مع أسماك القرش خلال "هروب السردين"
I know they don't see me as prey.
عرفت أنها لا تراني كفريسة.
However, I get bumped and tail-slapped just like any other guest
ومع ذلك، يتمّ صفعي كأي ضيف آخر
at this rowdy, rowdy banquet.
خلال هذه الوليمة الصاخبة جدّا.
From the shores of Africa we travel east,
من شواطئ افريقيا فلنسافر إلى الشرق،
across the vastness that is the Indian Ocean
حيث المحيط الهندي الشاسع
to the Maldives, an archipelago of coral islands.
إلى جزر المالديف، أرخبيل من الجزر المرجانية.
And during the stormy southwest monsoon,
وخلال الرياح الموسمية الجنوبية الغربية العاصفة،
manta rays from all across the archipelago
تُسافر أسماك شيطان البحر عبر الأرخبيل
travel to a tiny speck in Baa Atoll called Hanifaru.
إلى بقعة صغيرة في با أتول تُدعى هابيرو.
Armies of crustaceans,
مجموعات كبيرة من القشريات،
most no bigger than the size of your pupils,
لا يتجاوز حجم معظمها جحم حدقة العين،
are the mainstay of the manta ray's diet.
هي الغذاء الأساسي لأسماك شيطان البحر.
When plankton concentrations become patchy,
عندما تصبح كمية نباتات الطحلب ضئيلة،
manta rays feed alone
أسماك شيطان البحر تتغذى بمفردها
and they somersault themselves backwards again and again,
وتتشقلب عديد المرات حول نفسها،
very much like a puppy chasing its own tail.
مثل جرو صغير يُطارد ذيله.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
However, when plankton densities increase,
بينما، عندما ترتفع كمية نباتات الطحلب،
the mantas line up head-to-tail to form these long feeding chains,
تصطف أسماك شياطين البحر وراء بعضها البعض لتكون سلسلة
and any tasty morsel that escapes the first or second manta in line
غذائية طويلة وإن لم تستطع السمكة الأولى أكل الطعام
is surely to be gobbled up by the next or the one after.
فبالطبع ستستحوذ عليه السمكة الموالية.
As plankton levels peak in the bay,
كلما انخفضت كميات الطحالب بالخليج،
the mantas swim closer and closer together
كلما اقتربت أسماك شياطين البحر إلى بعضها البعض
in a unique behavior we call cyclone feeding.
وهو سلوك فريد من نوعه يُسمّى بالتغذية بشكل إعصار.
And as they swirl in tight formation,
وبما أنها تحوم في شكل ضيق،
this multi-step column of mantas
فإن هذه المجموعة من أسماك شياطين البحر
creates its own vortex, sucking in and delivering the plankton
تخلق نوعا من الإعصار، فتمتصّ الطحالب وتقدّمها
right into the mantas' cavernous mouths.
إلى أفواهها.
The experience of diving amongst such masses of hundreds of rays
إن تجربة الغوص ضمن المئات من أسماك شياطين البحر
is truly unforgettable.
هي حقّا تجربة فريدة من نوعها ولا تُنسى.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
When I first photographed Hanifaru,
عندما صورت هانيفارو أول مرة،
the site enjoyed no protection
هذه المنطقة لم تكن محمية
and was threatened by development.
وكانت مهدّدة بسبب التنمية.
And working with NGOs like the Manta Trust,
وبالعمل مع منظمات غير حكوميّة مثل "مانتا تراست"،
my images eventually helped Hanifaru
ساعدت صوري حتماً على أن
become a marine-protected area.
تصبح منطقة هانيفارو محمية.
Now, fisherman from neighboring islands,
حاليّا، الصيادون من جزر مجاورة،
they once hunted these manta rays
قاموا مرة بصيد أسماك شياطين البحر
to make traditional drums from their skins.
لصنع طبول تقليدية من جلد هذه الأسماك.
Today, they are the most ardent conservation champions
اليوم، هم من أكثر المحافظين المتحمسين
and manta rays earn the Maldivian economy
ويكسب الإقتصاد المالديفي بسبب أسماك شياطين البحر
in excess of 8 million dollars every single year.
ما يزيد عن 8 ملايين دولار كلّ سنة.
I have always wanted to travel back in time
لطالما أردت الرجوع بالزمن إلى الوراء
to an era where maps were mostly blank
في عصركانت فيه الخرائط معظمها فارغة
or they read, "There be dragons."
أو يقرأون، "هناك تنين"
And today, the closest I've come is visiting remote atolls
واليوم، أقرب مكان زرته هو الجزر النائية
in the western Indian Ocean.
في غرب المحيط الهندي.
Far, far away from shipping lanes and fishing fleets,
بعيدا عن ممرات الملاحة البحرية وأساطيل الصيد،
diving into these waters is a poignant reminder
الغوص في هذه المياه هو تذكير محرّك للمشاعر
of what our oceans once looked like.
لما كانت عليه محيطاتنا يوما ما.
Very few people have heard of Bassas da India,
عدد قليل من الناس سمع عن باساس دا أنديا،
a tiny speck of coral in the Mozambique Channel.
بقعة صغيرة من المرجان في قناة موزمبيق.
Its reef forms a protective outer barrier
هي شعب مرجانية تُمثّل حاجزا خارجيا واقيا
and the inner lagoon is a nursery ground
والبحيرة الداخلية هي عبارة عن مكان الحضانة
for Galapagos sharks.
لأسماك قرش غالاباغوس.
These sharks are anything but shy, even during the day.
كانت أسماك القرش تلك خجولة حتى خلال اليوم.
I had a bit of a hunch that they'd be even bolder
كان لدي إحساس بأنهم سيكونون أكثر جرأة
and more abundant at night.
ويرتفع عددهم في الليل.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Never before have I encountered
لم يسبق لي أن واجهت
so many sharks on a single coral outcrop.
العديد من أسماك القرش على نتوءات مرجانية.
Capturing and sharing moments like this --
تصوير لحظات كهذه ومشاركتها مع الجميع --
that reminds me why I chose my path.
يُذكّرني لما اخترت طريقي هذا.
Earlier this year, I was on assignment for National Geographic Magazine
في وقت ما خلال هذه السنة، كنت في مهمة لمجلة ناشيونال جيوغرافيك
in Baja California.
في ولاية باجا كاليفورنيا.
And about halfway down the peninsula on the Pacific side
وعلى حوالي منتصف الطريق إلى أسفل شبه الجزيرة على جانب المحيط الهادي
lies San Ignacio Lagoon,
تقع سان إغناسيو لاجون،
a critical calving ground for gray whales.
وهي مكان لولادة الحيتان الرمادية.
For 100 years, this coast was the scene of a wholesale slaughter,
لمدة 100 سنة، شهد هذا الساحل مذبحة،
where more than 20,000 gray whales were killed,
حيث قُتل أكثر من 20000 من الحيتان الرمادية،
leaving only a few hundred survivors.
ولم يتبق سوى بضع المئات من الناجين.
Today the descendents of these same whales
اليوم أحفاد نفس تلك الحيتان
nudge their youngsters to the surface
تدفع بأبنائها الصغار إلى السطح
to play and even interact with us.
للعب وحتى التفاعل معنا.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
This species truly has made a remarkable comeback.
لقد شهدت هذه الأنواع حقا عودة ملحوظة.
Now, on the other side of the peninsula lies Cabo Pulmo,
الآن، على الجانب الآخر من شبه الجزيرة تقع كابو بلمو،
a sleepy fishing village.
وهي جزيرة صيد هادئة.
Decades of overfishing had brought them close to collapse.
تسببت عقود من الصيد العشوائي في الإنهيار.
In 1995, local fisherman convinced the authorities
في سنة 1995، أقنع الصيادون المحليون السلطات
to proclaim their waters a marine reserve.
بالإعلان عن مياهها كمحمية بحرية.
But what happened next was nothing short of miraculous.
ولكن ما حدث بعد ذلك كان لا يقل عن معجزة.
In 2005, after only a single decade of protection,
ففي سنة 2005، بعد عقد واحد فقط من الحماية،
scientists measured the largest recovery of fish ever recorded.
قام العلماء بقياس مدى استرجاع الأسماك.
But don't take my word for it -- come with me.
ولكن لا تسمعوا كلمة مني-- تعالوا معي.
On a single breath, swim with me in deep,
بنفس واحد فقط، غوصوا معي في أعماق،
into one of the largest and densest schools of fish
أحد أكبر الأماكن لتواجد الأسماك
I have ever encountered.
التي واجهتها في أي وقت مضى.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
We all have the ability to be creators of hope.
لدينا جميعا القدرة على خلق نوع من الأمل.
And through my photography,
ومن خلال تصويري،
I want to pass on the message that it is not too late for our oceans.
أريد أن أنشر رسالة وهي: لم يفت الوقت لحماية محيطاتنا.
And particularly, I want to focus on nature's resilience
وأريد أن أركز خاصة على ، مرونة وسهولة تكيف الطبيعة
in the face of 7.3 billion people.
بمواجهة 7.3 مليار نسمة.
My hope is that in the future,
أملي أنني في المستقبل،
I will have to search much, much harder
سأبحث أكثر فأكثر
to make photographs like this,
للقيام بصور كهذه،
while creating images that showcase
وخلق صور تُظهر
our respectful coexistence with the ocean.
تعايشنا المحترم مع المحيط.
Those will hopefully become an everyday occurrence for me.
وآمل أن تصبح حدثاً يومياً بالنسبة لي.
To thrive and survive in my profession,
فللازدهار والبقاء على قيد الحياة في مهنتي،
you really have to be a hopeless optimist.
عليك حقا أن تكون متفائلا فاقدا للأمل.
And I always operate on the assumption
وأن تعمل دائما على فرضية
that the next great picture that will effect change
أن الصورة الرائعة التي ستحدث تغييرا
is right around the corner,
هي فقط قريبة جدا،
behind the next coral head,
خلف المرجان التالي،
inside the next lagoon
داخل البحيرة التالية
or possibly, in the one after it.
أو ربما في البحيرة التي تليها.
(Music)
(موسيقى)